let set12 =
    [
        {
            question: `#1. Consider the following statements in the context of microorganisms and diseases caused by them: \n 1. Chicken pox and Hepatitis A are caused by virus. \n 2. Typhoid and Measles are caused by bacteria. \n 3. Diarrhoea and Malaria are caused by protozoa. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. 1 only',
                    'B. 2 only',
                    'C. 1 and 3 only',
                    'D. 1, 2 and 3',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: C`,
            exp: `Explanation: Measles is not caused by bacteria, but virus. Common \n cold, influenza and most coughs are caused by viruses. In animals, \n foot and mouth disease of cattle is also caused by virus. \n Some microorganisms, disease caused by them and the mode of \n transmission: \n Disease Causative microorganism Mode of transmission \n Measles Virus Air \n Chickenpox Virus Air/Direct \n Polio Virus Air/Water \n Hepatitis A Virus Water \n Tuberculosis Bacteria Air \n Cholera Bacteria Water/Food \n Typhoid Bacteria Water \n Malaria Protozoa Mosquito \n Diarrhoea Protozoa Water`
        },
        {
            question: `#2. Consider the following: \n 1. Algae: Spirogyra \n 2. Protozoa: Chlamydomonas \n 3. Fungi: Rhizopus (bread mould) \n Which of the pairs given above is/are correctly matched?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. 1 only',
                    'B. 1 and 3 only',
                    'C. 3 only',
                    'D. 1, 2 and 3',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: B`,
            exp: `Explanation:  Of the given microorganisms, Spirogyra and Chlamydomonas are  examples of algae. Common examples of protozoa are amoeba and  paramecium. Rhizopus (bread mould), Penicillium and Aspergillus are  examples of fungi.  Microorganisms can be unicellular, like bacteria; some are  multicellular, like algae and fungi. Some microorganisms are  dependent on other microorganisms (parasitic), while some are not  (free living). Microorganisms like amoeba live alone (solitary) while  fungi lives in groups (colonial).`
        },
        {
            question: `#3. Which of the following microorganisms is required to turn milk into curd?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. Bacteria',
                    'B. Fungi',
                    'C. Virus',
                    'D. None of the above',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: A`,
            exp: `Explanation: Bacteria is required to turn milk into curd. Many microorganisms are found in curd, of which, a microorganism called Lactobacillus plays primary role. It multiplies in milk and converts it into curd.,  Microorganisms are helpful in the production of many food Items like cheese, bread etc.`
        },
        {
            question: `#4. Which of the following is produced by yeast through respiration, when it is mixed with food items?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. Oxygen',
                    'B. Carbon dioxide',
                    'C. Nitrogen',
                    'D. None of these',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: B`,
            exp: `Explanation: Once mixed with food items, yeast multiplies quickly to give out carbon dioxide through respiration. Carbon dioxide bubbles enhance the volume of the food item. Yeast is used in the baking industry, to make bread, pastry, cake, etc.`
        },
        {
            question: `#5. Match the items in Column 1 with those in Column 2, and choose the correct option. \n Column 1 Column 2 \n Fermentation Robert Koch \n Penicillin Edward Jenner \n Vaccine for measles Louis Pasteur,  \n Bacillus anthracis Alexander Fleming`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. 3 4 2 1',
                    'B. 3 4 1 2',
                    'C. 4 3 2 1',
                    'D. 4 3 1 2',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: A`,
            exp: `Explanation: The process of conversion of sugar into alcohol is called fermentation. Louis Pasteur discovered fermentation in 1857. Penicillin was discovered by Alexander Fleming in the year 1929. It is an antibiotic which destroys the disease causing organisms. Streptomycin, terramycin and erythromycin are some of the commonly used antibiotics; which are produced from fungi and bacteria. Vaccine for measles was invented by Edward Jenner in 1798. If dead or inactive microorganisms are injected into the body, then the cells of the body release antibodies according to the microorganisms. This concept is the basis for the production of vaccines.,  Robert Koch discovered Bacillus anthracis in the year 1876, which is the causative organism of anthrax. Anthrax is a dangerous disease affecting humans and animals.`
        },
        {
            question: `#6. Consider the following pairs: \n Disease Disease Carrier \n 1. Cholera Housefly \n 2. Malaria Female Aedes mosquito \n 3. Dengue Female Anopheles \n Which of the pairs given above is/are correctly matched?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. 1 only',
                    'B. 1 and 3 only',
                    'C. 2 and 3 only',
                    'D. 1, 2 and 3',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: A`,
            exp: `Explanation: Housefly acts as the carrier of cholera. Female Anopheles mosquito is an example of carrier of the malaria parasite (Plasmodium).,  Female Aedes mosquito is a carrier of the dengue virus.`
        },
        {
            question: `#7. Consider the following pairs: Plant disease Causative microorganism \n 1. Lemon canker Bacteria \n 2. Rust of wheat Fungi \n 3. Yellowing of ladyfinger Virus \n Which of the pairs given above is/are correctly matched?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. 1 only',
                    'B. 2 only',
                    'C. 3 only',
                    'D. 1, 2 and 3',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: D`,
            exp: `Explanation: Plant disease Causative organism Mode of transmission Lemon canker Bacteria Air Rust of wheat Fungi Air and seeds,  Yellowing of ladyfinger Virus Insects`
        },
        {
            question: `#8. Consider the following statements regarding food preservatives. \n 1. Sodium Benzoate and Sodium Metabisulfite are common food preservatives. \n 2. Salt, sugar, edible oil and vinegar are used as food preservatives. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. 1 only',
                    'B. 2 only',
                    'C. Both 1 and 2',
                    'D. Neither 1 nor 2',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: C`,
            exp: `Explanation: Microorganisms contaminate food items. Preservatives are used to prevents the contamination of food items. Sodium Benzoate and Sodium Metabisulfite are common food preservatives. These chemicals are used for the manufacture of jams and squash. Salt, sugar, edible oil and vinegar are used to inhibit the multiplication of microorganisms in food items. For example, salt, edible oil and vinegar are used to prevent the contamination of,  pickles; and sugar is used to prevent the contamination of jams and squash.`
        },
        {
            question: `#9. Consider the following statements regarding pasteurised milk. \n 1. Pasteurised milk can be consumed without boiling, because it is free of microorganisms. \n 2. In order to pasteurise the milk, it is first heated to a temperature of 70 degree celsius, for 15-20 minutes; and then cooled rapidly; and packaged. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. 1 only',
                    'B. 2 only',
                    'C. Both 1 and 2',
                    'D. Neither 1 nor 2',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: A`,
            exp: `Explanation: Pasteurised milk can be consumed without boiling, because it is free from microorganisms. To pasteurise the milk, it is heated up to 70 degree celsius for 15- 20 seconds and then cooled rapidly; and then stored or packaged. This decreases the multiplication of microorganisms. Thus, Louis Pasteur invented this method; hence it is named after him., `
        },
        {
            question: `#10. Which of the following statements is not correct, in regard to nitrogen cycle?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. Bacteria and blue green algae present in the soil, fix atmospheric nitrogen and convert it to nitrogen compounds, to be used by the plants.',
                    'B. Animals feeding on plants get proteins synthesised by them and other nitrogen compounds.',
                    'C. When plants and animals die, bacteria and fungi present in the soil convert the nitrogenous wastes into nitrogenous compounds to be used by plants again.',
                    'D. Certain other bacteria convert some part of them to nitrogen gas which goes back into the atmosphere.',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: D`,
            exp: `Explanation: The atmospheric nitrogen cannot be taken directly by plants and animals. Certain bacteria and blue green algae present in the soil fix nitrogen from the atmosphere and convert into compounds of nitrogen. Once nitrogen is converted into these usable compounds, it can be utilised by plants from the soil through their root system. Nitrogen is then used for the synthesis of plant proteins and other compounds. Animals feeding on plants get these proteins and other nitrogen compounds. When plants and animals die, bacteria and fungi,  present in the soil convert the nitrogenous wastes into nitrogenous compounds to be used by plants again. Certain other bacteria convert some part of them to nitrogen gas which goes back into the atmosphere. As a result, the percentage of nitrogen in the atmosphere remains more or less constant. Hence, statement 4 is incorrect. Nitrogen is an essential component of all living organisms, present in proteins, chlorophyll, nucleic acid and vitamins.`
        }
    ]